Frances Gillmor papers, 1910-1993 (Bulk 1930-1973)
University of Arizona Libraries, Special Collections
Frances Gillmor papers, 1910-1993 (Bulk 1930-1973).
MS 333
Gillmor, Frances, 1903-
Papers, 1910-1993, of professor and folklorist Frances Gillmor. Contains biographical materials, diaries, correspondence, research materials, published and unpublished manuscripts and articles, slides, photographs, and audio tapes documenting Gillmor's literary pursuits, scholarly activities and her wide ranging research in folklore and Southwestern culture.
23 linear ft.
University of Arizona Libraries, Special Collections University of Arizona PO Box 210055 Tucson, AZ 85721-0055 Phone: 520-621-6423 Fax: 520-621-9733 URL: http://speccoll.library.arizona.edu/
Restrictions
None.
Biographical Note
Frances Gillmor was born on May 21, 1903, in Buffalo, New York. The only child of Abner Churchill Gillmor and Annie McVicar Gillmor, she grew up in Brockton, Massachusetts and St. George, New Brunswick. She enrolled in the University of Chicago in 1921, but withdrew two years later to pursue her interest in journalism in Palm Beach and St. Augustine, Florida. In 1926 her family moved to Arizona, where Gillmor developed an interest in the culture of the Southwest and its Native American communities. She resumed her college education at the University of Arizona, and earned a B.A. in English from the University in 1928. The English Department offered Gillmor a teaching assistantship upon her graduation, and she began teaching courses in English and creative writing. She also began work on a graduate degree, and received her M.A. in English in 1931. In 1934, after serving as an instructor in English at the University of New Mexico for two years, she accepted a position as professor in the English Department of the University of Arizona, where she would remain for the next 40 years. During the ensuing decades she would pursue a variety of academic and intellectual interests. Her interest in Native American culture led her to Mexico to study Spanish. In 1938 she began studying Aztec codices at the Instituto de Filosofia y Letras. She began work on a biography of the Aztec king Nezahualcoyotl, which would culminate in the 1949 publication of The Flute of the Smoking Mirror. She continued her formal study, and received the Doctora en Letras from the Universidad Nacional Autónoma de México in 1957.
Gillmor loved to write, a fact reflected in her numerous literary publications. Before ultimately devoting all her attention to her academic writings, she pursued active interests in belles lettres and reportage. Her first novel, Thumbcap Weir (1929), drew on the experiences of her youth in New Brunswick, Canada. Windsinger (1930), and the adaptation of her M.A. thesis, Traders to the Navajo (1934), reveal her interest in Native American culture. Her third novel, Fruit Out of Rock (1940) describes life on an Arizona ranch. In 1937 she took up her journalistic pen again to cover the Trotsky trial in Mexico City for the Tucson, Arizona newspaper The Arizona Daily Star.
She received wide recognition for the quality of her work. A Guggenheim Fellowship awarded in 1959 allowed her to pursue her research interests in Spain. In 1962 she was named a Fellow of the American Folklore Society. In 1969 she received the University of Arizona Alumni Association’s Faculty Achievement Award, and the University officially recognized her classroom abilities by giving her its Creative Teaching Award in 1970. After her retirement from the University in 1973, she remained active as a scholar, continuing to write and contribute to the study of folklore. Frances Gillmor died on October 28, 1993.
The following sources contain additional biographical information: Virginia Rodriguez Rivera, Mujeres folkloristas (Mexico City: Universidad Nacional Autonoma de México, 1967); Who’s Who in the West, 15th ed., (Chicago: Marquis, 1976). Women Anthropologists: a Biographical Dictionary (New York: Greenwood Press, 1988).
Organization
This collection is organized into eight series.
Series I: Biographical Materials, 1914-1993
Series II: Diaries, 1910-1916
Series III: Correspondence, 1917-1993
Series IV: Stories, Poetry, Essays, 1910-1978
Series V: Student Notes and Papers, 1920s
Series VI: Research Notes, 1930s-1970s
Series VII: Audio Materials, 1950s-1970s
Series VIII: Photographs and Visual Materials, 1903-1991
Scope and Content Note
The collection documents Frances Gillmor's academic research and activities from 1930 through 1973, and includes her research notes from her field work in Mexico and Spain, including tape-recorded interviews and photographs. The collection contains Gillmor's personal and professional correspondence. Correspondents include the folklorists and historians Albert William Bork, R.S. Boggs, N. Ross Crumrine, J. Frank Dobie, Henry F. Dobyns, Fernando Horcasitas and others. The collection includes correspondence with publishers of her books, and with her literary agents. It includes typescripts and manuscript materials of numerous unpublished manuscripts, and the “first version” of her novel Fruit Out of Rock.
Gillmor, Frances, 1903-; Apenes, Ola, 1898-1943 -- Correspondence.; Bork, Albert William -- Correspondence.; Boggs, Ralph Steele, 1901- -- Correspondence.; Crumrine, N. Ross -- Correspondence.; Dobie, J. Frank (James Frank), 1888-1964 -- Correspondence.; Dobyns, Henry F. -- Correspondence.; Hand, Wayland Debs, 1907- -- Correspondence.; Hellbom, Anna-Britta, 1919- -- Correspondence.; Horcasitas, Fernando -- Correspondence.; Kinzhalov, R. V. -- Correspondence.; Ramos Pérez, Demetrio -- Correspondence.; Ramos Gómez, Luis Javier -- Correspondence.; Stone, Marti -- Correspondence.; Wetherill, Luisa Wade -- Correspondence.; Wetherill, John -- Correspondence.; Women authors -- Arizona -- Tucson -- Archives.; Women college teachers -- Arizona -- Tucson -- Archives.; Women folklorists -- Arizona -- Tucson -- Archives.; Authors -- Arizona -- Tucson -- Archives.; College teachers -- Arizona -- Tucson -- Archives.; Folklorists -- Arizona -- Tucson -- Archives.; Folklore -- Arizona.; Folklore -- Mexico.; Folklore -- Spain.; Folklore -- Southwest, New.; American Folklore Society -- Correspondence.; Drama de la pasion.; Pastores.; Tastoanes.; Folk drama, Spanish.; Mexican drama.; Passion-plays.; Christmas plays, Mexican.; Christmas plays, Spanish.; Indian dance -- Mexico.; Moros y Cristianos (Dance); Audio tapes.; Field notes.; Manuscripts for publication.; Photographs.; Slides (Photographs).
Container List
- Series I: Biographical Materials, 1914-1993.
  Contains personal data related to her family and career, including copies of resumes and bibliographies prepared by Gillmor, short autobiographical sketches, and scrapbooks from her primary and secondary school years. This series includes a cassette tape recording of a memorial service held in her honor in 1993. The scrapbooks include mounted photographs. (See also the series Photographs and Visual Materials for additional photographs of Gillmor.)
  - Biographical materials, 1921-1991. (Box 1, Folder 1-4)
  - Biographical materials; degree Doctora en Letras, 1957-1958 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Frances Gillmor memorial, Grace Episcopal Church, Tucson, [cassette tape] Nov. 7, 1993 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Scrapbook (school days), ca. 1914-1921 (Box 1, Folder 7)
- Series II: Diaries, 1910-1916
  Three bound diary books with entries written between 1910 and 1916.
  - Diaries, November 15, 1910 - December 31, 1915 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Diary, May 21, 1916 - December 1916 (Box 2, Folder 2)
- Series III: Correspondence, 1917-1993
  Personal and professional correspondence. Included is correspondence with folklorists and historians such as Ola and Georg Apenes, R.S. Boggs, N. Ross Crumrine, J. Frank Dobie, Wayland Hand, Fernando Horcasitas, and others. Also correspondence with her literary agents and publishers, such as Editorial Diana, Houghton-Mifflin, Putnams Sons and several university presses. Also includes correspondence with Louisa and John Wetherill, whose lives she chronicled in her M.A. thesis, and correspondence with members of the Royal Norwegian Air Force in connection with her unpublished work Norway on Their Shoulders, concerning Norwegians in exile in Canada during World War II.
  - General A, 1955-1989 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - American Folklore Society, 1970-1978 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Apenes, Ola, and family, 1942-1983. (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Arora, Shirley, 1975 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - General B, 1947-1983 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Boggs, R.S., 1948-1973 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Bork, Bill, 1957-1987 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - General C, 1939-1990 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Correspondence; contracts and copyrights, 1928-1981 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Crumrine, N. Ross, 1979-1983 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - General D-E, 1955-1989 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Dobie, J. Frank, 1935-1951 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Dobyns, Henry, 1969-1977 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Duell, Sloan and Pierce, Inc., 1939-1955 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Editorial Diana, 1967-1974 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - General F-G, 1929-1989 (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Fellowship correspondence, 1948-1967 (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Flute of the Smoking Mirror correspondence, 1942-1966 (Box 4, Folder 1-3)
  - Gillmor family estate correspondence, 1917-1983 (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - General H, 1943-1984 (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - Hand, Wayland, 1946-1976 (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - Hellbom, Anna-Britta, 1968-1991 (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - Horcasitas, Fernando, 1967-1980 (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - Houghton-Mifflin, 1932-1933 (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - Houghton-Mifflin, 1934-1951 (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - General I-J, 1954-1993 (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - International Congress of Americanists, 1964, 1979 (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - Joseph, Nannine, 1943. (Box 5, Folder 7)
  - General K-L, 1945-1979 (Box 5, Folder 8)
  - Kinzholov, R.V., 1970-1981 (Box 5, Folder 9)
  - Latin American Institute of Folklore, 1967 (Box 5, Folder 10)
  - General M, 1944-1993 (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - General N-O, 1934-1991 (Box 6, Folder 2)
  - Norway on Their Shoulders correspondence, 1943-1974 (Box 6, Folder 3-4)
  - General P, 1955-1976 (Box 6, Folder 5)
  - Putnams Sons, 1928-1939 (Box 6, Folder 6)
  - General R, 1948-1991 (Box 6, Folder 7)
  - Ramos, Demetrio (includes Luis-Javier Ramos Gomez), 1968-1974 (Box 6, Folder 8)
  - Reunion Sobre Antropología y Historia del Noroeste, 1974 (Box 6, Folder 9)
  - Royal Norwegian Air Force, 1943-1945 (Box 7, Folder 1)
  - General S, 1949-1989 (Box 7, Folder 2)
  - Southwest Folklore, 1979-1981 (Box 7, Folder 3)
  - Stone, Martha (includes Martita Boyle), 1967-1983 (Box 7, Folder 4)
  - General T, 1949-1976 (Box 7, Folder 5)
  - General U, 1955-1973 (Box 7, Folder 6)
  - University of Arizona, 1952-1983 (Box 7, Folder 7)
  - University of Arizona. Sonora Committee minutes, 1958; 1966 (Box 8, Folder 1)
  - University of Arizona. Sonora Committee projects, 1955-1966 (Box 8, Folder 2)
  - University of Arizona. Folklore Committee, 1943-1971 (Box 8, Folder 3)
  - University of Arizona Press, 1966-1983 (Box 8, Folder 4)
  - University of California Press, 1975-1979 (Box 8, Folder 5)
  - University of New Mexico Press, 1949-1982 (Box 8, Folder 6)
  - University of Utah Press, 1976-1983 (Box 8, Folder 7)
  - General W-Z, 1949-1991 (Box 8, Folder 8)
  - Wetherill, Louisa Wade, and John Wetherill (Box 9, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence to and from unidentified persons (Box 9, Folder 2)
- Series IV: Stories, Poetry, Essays, 1910-1978.
  - Stories, 1910-1915 (Box 9, Folder 3)
  - Poetry, ca. 1920-1928 (Box 9, Folder 4)
  - Newspaper articles written for the St. Augustine Evening Record, ca. 1925 (Box 9, Folder 5)
  - Short stories, essays, book reviews, 1927-1928 (Box 9, Folder 6)
  - Short stories, student papers, 1920s (Box 9, Folder 7)
  - "Commission of Inquiry into the Charges Made Against Leon Trotsky in the Moscow Trials", 1937 (Box 9, Folder 8)
    Contains versions of published and unpublished stories, poetry and essays, and newspaper reporting. Major manuscripts include an early typescript version of her novel Fruit Out of Rock, a typescript of the unpublished manuscript Norway on Their Shoulders, written ca. 1944, and a typescript with manuscript corrections of the unpublished work Navajo. Also includes manuscript materials for her research on the folk drama Moros y cristianos.
  - Fruit Out of Rock, first version [typescript] (Box 9, Folder 9-10)
  - Hyacinth, the Book Writing Buick [typescript], 1950 (Box 10, Folder 1)
  - Moors y Cristianos [sic] in Mexico [manuscript materials] (Box 10, Folder 2-3)
  - Navajo, [typescript, with manuscript corrections], 1951 (Box 10, Folder 4)
  - Notes for Norway on Their Shoulders (Box 10, Folder 5)
  - Norway on Their Shoulders, [typescript], 1944 (Box 10, Folder 6)
  - Miscellaneous unpublished manuscripts [typescripts] (Box 10, Folder 7)
- Series V: Student Notes and Papers, 1920s
  Class notes and papers from Gillmor’s undergraduate courses at the University of Arizona.
  - Student notes and papers, 1920s (Box 11, Folder 1-4)
- Series VI: Research Notes, 1930s-1970s
  - Subseries I: General Notes
    Contains general research notes from Gillmor’s scholarly activities as folklorist and educator. Includes notes from her study of early Mexican history, Nahua codices and the Aztec language. This series includes some notes on Los tastoanes. The Photographs and Visual Materials series includes five oversized manuscript chronological charts created by Gillmor during her study of early Mexican chronology.
    - Bibliographies of Frances Gillmor's works (Box 11, Folder 5)
    - Reviews of works by Frances Gillmor (Box 12, Folder 1)
    - Notes on prehispanic archaeology and architecture (Box 12, Folder 2)
    - Mexican art school, 1949 (Box 12, Folder 3)
    - Mexican writing system notes from lecture by Charles Dibble (Box 12, Folder 4)
    - Notes on Aztec language (Box 12, Folder 5)
    - Interpretation of the Xolotle Codex by Charles Dibble (Box 12, Folder 6)
    - Notes on charts, codex illustrations (Box 12, Folder 7)
    - Miscellaneous notes on Mexican ancient history (Box 12, Folder 8)
    - Notes on calendar codices; Alfonso Caso lecture (Box 12, Folder 9)
    - Nahuatl vocabulary, ca. 1939 (Box 13, Folder 1)
    - Barlow payment for Xochipala, Guerro; landanza de Santiago; other Barlow notes (Box 13, Folder 2)
    - Chinese folklore bibliography (Box 13, Folder 3)
    - Folklore Institute of America, 1946 (Box 13, Folder 4)
    - Notes on Indian topics (Box 13, Folder 5)
    - Latin American Summer Institute of Folklore, 1967 (Box 13, Folder 6)
    - Lectures and notes on talks (Box 13, Folder 7)
    - Liberal arts lectures (Box 14, Folder 1)
    - Mexican combat plays, symbolism and masking (Box 14, Folder 2)
    - Midcentury folklore symposium (Box 14, Folder 3)
    - Motif index questionnaire (Box 14, Folder 4)
    - Memorial University of Newfoundland motif index project (Box 14, Folder 5)
    - Tale motifing project: Arizona originals (Box 14, Folder 6)
    - Miscellaneous notes (Box 14, Folder 7)
    - Reading lists for American literature and Southwestern literature courses (Box 14, Folder 8)
    - Southern Arizona stuff (Box 14, Folder 9)
    - Notebooks--Spain (and Scotland, Norway, Sweden and Finland addresses) (Box 14, Folder 10)
    - Los tastoanes papers, Latin American Folklore Conference, University of California, Los Angeles (Box 14, Folder 11)
    - Los tastoanes, attitudes toward (Box 15, Folder 1)
    - Address books (Box 15, Folder 2)
    - Miscellaneous material (Box 15, Folder 3)
    - Copy of the Christian B. Apenes festschrift Christian B. Apenes: til 70-årsdagen 19. februar 1972, February 1972 (Box 15, Folder 4)
    - Gross, Hildegard. A Study of Folklore Books in Corbett Elementary School Library [student paper] (Box 15, Folder 5)
    - Magnetic Evolution of the Human Soul (Box 15, Folder 6)
    - Webb, George. Naco [unpublished typescript] (Box 15, Folder 7)
  - Subseries II: Mexico.
    Research notes from fieldwork in Mexico. The bulk of the notes relate to Gillmor’s research in Mexican folk dramas and dances. Some folders include photographic materials and tape recordings. (For additional audio and photographic materials see the series Audio Materials and Photographs and Visual Materials).
    - Arispe (Box 15, Folder 8)
    - Atemejac del Valle; La conquista (Box 15, Folder 9)
    - Atlixco, Puebla; Historia de Carlemagno (Horcasitas manuscript) (Box 15, Folder 10)
    - Caborca; Los pastores (Box 15, Folder 11)
    - Cajititlan; Fiesta de los reyes (Box 16, Folder 1-2)
    - Cajititlan; La conquista (Box 16, Folder 3)
    - Cajititlan; Los moros y christianos (Box 16, Folder 4)
    - Cajititlan; Los pastores (Box 16, Folder 5-6)
    - Calzontzin [Michoacán, Mexico]; interview with Doña Casiona Torral (Box 16, Folder 7)
    - Chiapas (Box 16, Folder 8)
    - Cuilapan (Box 16, Folder 9)
    - Cuilapan (San Juan barrio); fiesta of greased pole (Box 16, Folder 10)
    - Cuilapan (Box 16, Folder 11)
    - Cuilapan [Oaxaca, Mexico]; La conquista de México (Box 17, Folder 1)
    - Cuilapan; Quaderno de danse de pluma (Box 17, Folder 2)
    - Guadalajara; Episcopal Church in Mexico (Box 17, Folder 3)
    - Guadalajara; La conquista (Box 17, Folder 4)
    - Guadalajara (Box 17, Folder 5)
    - Guadalajara; interview; La aquila negra (Box 17, Folder 6)
    - Guadalajara; Lomas de Paradero; La conquista de la cruz verde [#1] (Box 17, Folder 7)
    - Guadalajara; Lomas de Paradero; La conquista de la cruz verde [#2] (Box 18, Folder 1)
    - Pictures in / around Guadalajara (Box 18, Folder 2)
    - Guadalajara; Los pastores (Box 18, Folder 3)
    - Guadalajara; Tlaquepaque; La conquista (Box 18, Folder 4)
    - Guadelupe; Villa de fiesta, 12 December 1967. (Box 18, Folder 5)
    - Guaymas (Box 18, Folder 6)
    - Hermosillo; Los pastores (Box 18, Folder 7)
    - Hermosillo; Los cuatro apariciones (Box 18, Folder 8)
    - Hermosillo; Dia de la Santa Cruz; Las matachinas (Box 18, Folder 9)
    - Hermosillo; Alabansas (Box 18, Folder 10)
    - Hermosillo and environs [maps] (Box 18, Folder 11)
    - Hermosillo; correspondence, plays, matape (Box 18, Folder 12)
    - Hermosillo [photographs, negatives] (Box 19, Folder 1)
    - Hermosillo [audio tape only] (Box 19, Folder 2)
    - Huejokingo; Drama de la pasion (Box 19, Folder 3)
    - Ixcatan; Los tastoanes (Box 19, Folder 4)
    - Ixtapalapa (Box 19, Folder 5)
    - Ixtapalapa; Amecameca; Chalma (Box 19, Folder 6)
    - Ixtapalapa; Drama de la pasion (Box 20, Folder 1)
    - Ixtapalapa; Moors and Christians (Box 20, Folder 2)
    - Jocotán; Los tastoanes (Box 20, Folder 3)
    - Jocotán; Los tastoanes [taped interviews and notes] (Box 20, Folder 4)
    - Jocotán; Los tastoanes (Box 20, Folder 5)
    - Jocotepec (Box 20, Folder 6)
    - Matape; El paso del los santos reyes [text] (Box 20, Folder 7)
    - Matape; El paso del los santos reyes (Box 21, Folder 1)
    - Matape; Moors and Christians (Box 21, Folder 2)
    - Matape; Semana santa; La representación de la pasión (Box 21, Folder 3-4)
    - Maya (and Crumrine materials) (Box 21, Folder 5)
    - Maya; Victoria Reifler Bricker offprint and correspondence (Box 21, Folder 6)
    - Mexicaltitlan [photographs], ca. 1967 (Box 21, Folder 7)
    - Michoacán; Dia de los muertos, 1967 (Box 21, Folder 8)
    - Milpa; Alta relaciones y las pastoricitas and Los vaqueros (Box 21, Folder 9)
    - Nextipac [Jalisco, Mexico]; interview; Don Damien (Box 22, Folder 1)
    - Oaxaca; El codice Gracida Dominicano; Los lunes del cerro (Box 22, Folder 2)
    - Paricutin; El dia de los muertos, 1967 (Box 22, Folder 3)
    - Paricutin; volcano villages (Box 22, Folder 4-6)
    - Paricutin; volcano villages (Box 23, Folder 1)
    - Patzcuaro [Michoacán, Mexico] (Box 23, Folder 2)
    - Peñón de los Banos [Mexico, D.F.]; Drama de Cinco de Mayo en el Peñón (Box 23, Folder 3)
    - Piedra Imán (Box 23, Folder 4)
    - Sahuayo (Box 23, Folder 5-6)
    - Salamanca; El triunfo de la inocencia en los campos de Belen (Box 23, Folder 7)
    - Salatitán [text and interviews] (Box 23, Folder 8)
    - San Ignacio; Coloquio de pastores (Box 24, Folder 1)
    - San Juan [Ocotan, Mexico]; Los tastoanes [text, interview] (Box 24, Folder 2)
    - San Juan [Ocotan, Mexico]; Los pastores; los tastoanes (Box 24, Folder 3)
    - San Juan [Ocotan, Mexico]; renting the script (Box 24, Folder 4)
    - San Mateo Atenco; Drama de la pasion (Box 24, Folder 5)
    - San Pedro Cholula; Drama de los moros y cristianos; Danza de la pasion (Box 24, Folder 6)
    - Santa Ana Acatlan de Juarez (Box 24, Folder 7)
    - Santa Ana [near Toluca] (Box 24, Folder 8)
    - Santa Ana Tepetitlan [Jalisco, Mexico] (Box 24, Folder 9)
    - Teotitlan del Valle; plume dance; La conquista (Box 25, Folder 1-2)
    - Tonalá [Chiapas, Mexico]; Los tastoanes (Box 25, Folder 3)
    - Tonalá [Chiapas, Mexico]; Los tastoanes [tape reels] (Box 25, Folder 4)
    - Tonalá [Jalisco, Mexico]; La boda de los indios (Box 25, Folder 5)
    - Tonalá [Jalisco, Mexico]; Los pastores (Box 25, Folder 6)
    - Tonalá [Jalisco, Mexico]; San Isidro, 1968 (Box 25, Folder 7)
    - Notes on twins; El primer Montezuma legends in the southwestern United States (Box 25, Folder 8)
    - Tzintzuntzan; Drama de la pasion [photocopy], ca. 1631 (Box 25, Folder 9)
    - Urupan (Box 26, Folder 1)
    - Vera Cruz; interview with Dr. Rosaldo’s mother (Box 26, Folder 2)
    - Voladores (Box 26, Folder 3)
    - Zapopan (Box 26, Folder 4)
    - Zapopan; Juan Diego and the Virgin of Guadelupe (Box 26, Folder 5)
    - Zapopan; La conquista of Zapopan (Box 26, Folder 6)
    - Notebook with miscellaneous notes (Box 26, Folder 7)
    - Moros y cristianos unsorted (Box 26, Folder 8-9)
    - Moros y cristianos (general) (Box 26, Folder 10)
    - Danza de la conquista (Box 27, Folder 1)
    - Material on the use of conversation in Aztec names (Box 27, Folder 2)
    - Mexico (earlier material) (Box 27, Folder 3-4)
    - Mexico; Drama de la pasion (Box 27, Folder 5)
    - Drama de la pasion (Chimalhuacan, Amecameca, Ozumba, Tepoztlan) (Box 27, Folder 6)
  - Subseries III: United States, Europe, Philippines.
    Research notes concerning various folklore topics in southern Arizona and Europe. Includes notes from folklore archives in Scandinavian countries, and shepherd’s plays performed in Tucson, Arizona. Also includes a folder of material on Phillipines folklore. Some folders include photographic materials and tape recordings. (For additional audio and photographic materials see the series Audio Materials and Photographs and Visual Materials).
    - Tucson, Arizona; Los pastores (Box 27, Folder 7)
    - Tucson, Arizona; Pascua and Los pastores (Box 27, Folder 8)
    - San Xavier, Arizona; Tohono O’odham; All Saints, All Souls; Day of the Dead (Box 27, Folder 9)
    - Denmark; folklore archives (Box 27, Folder 10)
    - England; folk plays (Box 27, Folder 11)
    - Finland; folklore archives (Box 28, Folder 1)
    - Greece (Box 28, Folder 2)
    - Norway; folklore archives (Box 28, Folder 3)
    - [Phillipines]; Moro-moro, etc.; interview with Isadora Blancaflor (Box 28, Folder 4)
    - Poland (Box 28, Folder 5)
    - Sweden; folklore archives (Box 28, Folder 6)
  - Subseries IV: Spain.
    Research notes for Gillmor’s work in Spain on folk drama, collected on her trip to Spain in 1959-1960. Some folders include photographic materials and tape recordings. (For additional audio and photographic materials see the series Audio Materials and Photographs and Visual Materials).
    - Alberca, 1960 (Box 28, Folder 7)
    - Alcoy; Moors and Christians and contrabandistas embajada [two tape cartridges] (Box 28, Folder 8)
    - Alcoy [Alicante, Spain], 1959 (Box 29, Folder 1)
    - Alicante [includes photographs] (Box 29, Folder 2)
    - Almeria (Box 29, Folder 3)
    - Almuñecar (Box 29, Folder 4)
    - Atajate (Box 29, Folder 5)